so i have a suitor
in from the
nikaya 1060 girimananda 1060 girimananda
sutra
and it's about 10 perceptions that need
to be developed
the first one is
i'll just read the that's that first
section what is the perception of a
nietzsche that needs to be developed
that needs to be developed
here ubiku having gone to the forest to
the root of a tree an empty hut
reflects meditates
mata is a nature feeling is a nature
perception is a nietzsche
sankara is our nietzsche
consciousness is a nietzsche
he lives as one who sees a nature in the
right way
in these five assumed aggregates
so just to
the developing
these perceptions
is
meditation yes that begins
yes that begins
by going to an empty forest an empty
heart physically removed from people
physically removed from people
and obviously the prerequisite and
prerequisite for succeeding
in
living alone like that
is development in virtue
establishment diverge accomplishment in
virtue sense restraint and guiding of the sense
sense restraint and guiding of the sense
those
[Music] watchfulness and so on
watchfulness and so on
so that's where the meditation begins
and that's with your virtue
uh then the next step when when you are
thoroughly established in your precepts
and in guarding of the sense those is
that uh going to an empty forest
that's when these perceptions become
clearer when you're physically removed
when you're physically removed
and can then be developed then you can
start meditating so to speak exactly
a prerequisite for any of these
perceptions is physical removal from
people being alone
secluded in an empty forest empty heart
dwelling away
that's that's not uh not not optional
from unwholesome states
including some states
exactly but physically you have to have
been removed from from company from a
possibility of company from the
immediate possibility of company
like you know i might be alone in the
room but if somebody is next door to me
they can come and knock at any given
time or i could hear them at any given time
or i could hear them at any given time
or call me at any given time so you're
not really alone
that possibility is looming over
but when you're secluded in a you know
in a way that the suit is described it's
like okay now now you're secluded now
you know that
you know at least until tomorrow when
you get back to the village or something
there will be no people here you are
alone so you use that certain
so you use that certain
current facticity of being secluded
at the time
to ponder on the phenomenon of that that
universal nature of
being alone
the five aggregates being there in the
world on their own empty of owner empty
of controller empty of the master
uh and so you use that certain
current basis of actual factual
seclusion in fact or this room is empty
of others as the buddha says
so is these aggregates are empty
yourselves or something like that
similar but just to on in terms of in nature so
but just to on in terms of in nature so
being in seclusion being withdrawn from
unwholesome states
that perception becomes clearer
so you're not
you're not creating
a nature no not fabricating not
fabricating you're not imagining it
you're expanding your mind
in a in that peripheral sense where you
notice more and more until you notice
yeah any of the aggregates sitting there
on its own peripherally and during
because of which you have this
experience of being alone in the forest
or an empty heart at the moment
uh and then the characteristics of that
of that aggregate or all the five
aggregates or of the experience as a
whole or that body there
which i was understood peripherally will
be seen as yeah
impersonal unownable unownable
given
existing on its own
for what it is
and that's all forms of our nature
seeing a nature
so you're able then to see the nature of
this experience
experience
so why is that
nature of experience that perception of
a nature not obvious
to us
not obvious to everyone
well because people
people's minds
are not developed peripherally enough
they don't have enough context in
reality their own situation
because they're too absorbed with the
pull of sensuality with the avoidance of
pain where the
where the
practitious perpetuation of ownership
so clouding
clouding the perspective or just you
know as they would compare like you know
as they would compare like you know
living
uh immersed in a swamp in water
so for as long as
the lifestyle and livelihood doesn't
change um
um
whereby it stops perpetuating these
gratuitous assumptions
you can't see then what you would see if
you don't have those assumptions
so that's why you like i said many times
the practice of the dummy is not
something you can do on top of your life
like whatever
the practice of dhamma means
restructuring your life
so it matches the principles of
nature of the five aggregates before
it's too late
and the importance for matching those
principles is so that you can develop
this passion and remove the pictures
ownership of those very same aggregates
so it's not it's not something like a
uh
revelation you can get on top of your
currently sort of you know ordinary life
and then you just suddenly see this no
no
you need to start undoing everything
else that's covering it up right because
you can removing the cover-ups and the
entire life the entire human life is one
massive cover-up
of non-ownership of a nature of fear of
anxiety of death and everything else so
it's a giant camera
that's why people are addicted and
passionately dependent upon that life
because if they look you know what the
if they look you know what the
alternative is it's frightening it says
oh what if i'm not in control
but if you know being subject to death
is is something that you know
it's it's going to be experienced
individually internally and it's going to be very
internally and it's going to be very
unpleasant because everything that
is there to me and that i depend upon
will cease
will be taken away
yeah i don't i don't want to know that
so yeah exactly so it's too much to deal
with so it's better for me to basically
not acknowledge it and not want to know
about it yeah
enjoy life well and then you know you
might not necessarily enjoy life but by
choosing to ignore this then you're
already choosing the direction of trying
to enjoy life and pretend there is no
problem underneath
so that yeah again
you can understand it
intellectually i need you you can get
the dictionary definition
[Music] and you can understand it on that level
and you can understand it on that level
of information
but if you don't change your life
you'll never actually see it or discern
it no no no
the actual nature that's where you know
the physical actions need to be purified
the livelihood needs to be purified the
the whole like speech needs to be
purified the habits need to be you know
purified abandoned whatever else
and then all these things you did in the
suttas you'll have a basis to see them
within your experience
without it is just an abstract theory
and on the level of belief
faith and religion
basically something you take on as a
form of identity not not something
you're actually
internally cultivating yeah
yeah
and in terms of that in terms of
translation so nietzsche
so nietzsche
usually translated as impermanence
and it gives that sense of
just you know it won't be around for
very long yeah to change eventually
but it's not deep enough
it's not deep enough because it's it's
it's the term impermanence is kind of
or at least he has become too impersonal
so when you're saying permanence you
think it's any random impermanence of
any random thing
that's what a niche is but it's not
nietzsche remember that we found that in
in original sanskrit nitya means dear
personal intimate
so the whole nature the whole sense of
permanence durability
is bound without intimacy it's bound
with that ownership with that which is
dear to you
so a niche should be seen on that level
so that's what you're saying if you want
to practically see a niche you need to
find things that are there to you things
that you would not remain
sort of indifferent if they change those
things if they go away or if they change
and then contemplate them going away and
changing to see how much emotionally you're
to see how much emotionally you're
dependent on that and how much you're
refusing to accept the reality that they
are subject to change
they are subject to our nature that's it
so that's why translating as
impermanence i mean it's fine if if you
explain where
where
that impermanence is found
but if
you know if it's just impermanence of
everything and nothing that's not the
niche at all because it's not personal
enough i also like the translation of circumstantial
circumstantial
well again even that like um whichever
translation you choose i think you have
to explain it really yeah
because circumstantial people can then
interpret could possibly interpret as oh
this circumstantial thus
it's on my control that's not my
responsibility that's i can dismiss it
but your attachment isn't your
responsibility is in your control not
directly indirectly it's because of the
way you regard things you are attached
to them so
you are responsible for it
you know if you say oh i keep i don't
know drinking cold water non-stop and having
drinking cold water non-stop and having
headaches as a result of it
so yes you're not directly causing
yourself headaches
but if you stop drinking the water that is
if you stop drinking the water that is
very cold your headaches will go away
so you are responsible for them
indirectly you're not drinking water to get
you're not drinking water to get
headaches but they are the results
so your attachment to things that are
dear to you yeah you might want not to
be attached but you keep doing things
that attachment is the result of
that's what you're saying it's the
symptoms of the problem and the problem
is basically you acting out of passion
aversion and distraction
not taking responsibility on the level
of choice and certainly not having
developed virtue sufficiently enough
which is like you know a certain basis
they would already start challenging
your notion of
well self and ownership and things that
are dear to you
even just keeping the mere precepts
but if we if so if i think about the
plot the matter is
a nature
matter or feeling is
[Music] i would say mata is inaccessible inaccessible
[Music]
it's it's arisen circumstantially
through elements and
elements and
things that i
have no access to yeah
but again whether that's done as an
explanation or as
or as
or is that done as a description of what
you're peripherally seeing
correctly through mindfulness of the
body peripherally established
that's the difference pretty much
because if you're describing that body
that you see like right now while we
speak that body that you know the mouth
that's speaking in the form behind yeah
it's inaccessible it exists there and
i'm using it to express these thoughts
and so on
but if you're not aware of it
peripherally while we're speaking right
here right now using this mouth and this
form and so on then it just becomes an
explanation that then people can adopt
but it does not pertain to that which it
should pertain
so in other words it's just abstract
so that's why
rather than trying to figure out these
abstractions you won't understand the nietzsche
you won't understand the nietzsche
take on the precepts
god descends those you'll see why later
on
and then start
challenging things that are dear to you
not you don't need to destroy them or
get rid of them just contemplate their
cessation their destruction their change
being taken away
and when the anxiety arises and fear my
health as well yeah sure not just people
that are there to you and other things
things and items your own body is the
thing you know
your health your life everything that
depends on
and then when anxiety starts to come up
and fear and doubt
that's where you're going to see the
benefit of previously developed precepts
guarding of the sensors and sense
restraint that will keep together in
other words the aggregator virtually
developed beforehand
will be your container because yeah that
sense itself was going to start to rebel
and complain
and scream and kick because you're
dissolving it
through challenging its ownership
by developing that perception by yeah
by confining it within those perceptions
and i think when you when you start to
speak about a nietzsche
you can't help but
describe dukkha
describe it well and then yeah it's just
it's there it's there yeah it sounds
like the same
it's just different aspects of the same
thing because
because
seeing that unknown ability and subject
to change is felt unpleasantly
it like you know simultaneously with the
perception of a nietzsche it's a
simultaneous dukkha
it's not a second thing that follows
later so it's this it's the same facet it's
so it's this it's the same facet it's
the facet that's there at the same time
and then the experience of that anichi
dukkha cannot be mined cannot be atta
so
on the level of self-awareness of
nietzsche and dukkha
and dukkha
it's an utter
you cannot own it even if you want to
even if your sense of self is still
trying to assume the ownership and rebel
if you confine it within the perception
of vanity and dukkha and and endure it
within a nietzsche
that sense of self is fading it is it is
disintegrating it is wasting away
because it's it's unsustainable in that
environment